William H. Ryder Collection of Confederate History MS011
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Cartes de Visite - Photographs, 1770 -- 1890; MS011.001; 1.45 Linear Feet; 180 Digital Object(s)
  - Wilson, 1865 -- 1880; MS011.001.001.00161; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "Wilson; Ms. Vincent's husband." Produced by: Black & Case Photographic Artists, 163 & 173 Washington St., Boston & 2 Downings Block, Newport, R.I.
  - W. H. H. [William Henry Harrison] Murray, 1870 -- 1880; MS011.001.001.00162; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "W. H. H. Murray; Park St. Church." Produced by: J. Ward & Son, Publishers, 125 Washington St., Boston, Mass.
    Authors; cartes-de-visite; Murray, W. H. H. (William Henry Harrison), 1840-1904
  - Eliza Wethersby, 1870 -- 1880; MS011.001.001.00163; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "Wethersby; Burlesque." Produced by: Sarony, 680 Broadway.
    cartes-de-visite; Wethersby, Eliza
  - Mdlle. Nilsson [Christina], 1870; MS011.001.001.00164; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. Produced by: J. Gurney & Son, Fifth Avenue, Cor. 16th St, N.Y.
    Singers; cartes-de-visite; Nilsson, Christine
  - Prof. Tholuck [August], 1860 -- 1870; MS011.001.001.00165; Ullman, Sarah (Box 1)
    25. "Prof. Tholuck; Tholuck." Produced by: Vuagnat, Peintre Photograph, Gen&#00E8;ve.
    Professors; Theologians; cartes-de-visite; Tholuck, August, 1799-1877
  - Laboulaye [édouard René de], 1860 -- 1870; MS011.001.001.00166; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "Laboulaye." Produced by: Photographie du Grant Hôtel, Nadar, 35 Boulevart des Capucines.
    Poets; Authors; cartes-de-visite; Laboulaye, Édouard, 1811-1883
  - Kronprinz [Crown Prince Frederick III], 1860 -- 1870; MS011.001.001.00167; Unknown (Box 1)
    Emperors; cartes-de-visite; Frederick III, German Emperor, 1831-1888
  - I. A. [Isaak August] Dorner, 1865 -- 1880; MS011.001.001.00168; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "I. A. Dorner." Produced by: Loescher & Petsch, Berlin, Atelier, Leipziger-Straße 132, Eingang im Mittel-Portal.
    cartes-de-visite; Dorner, I. A. (Isaak August), 1809-1884
  - C. [Constantin von] Tischendorf, 1865 -- 1875; MS011.001.001.00169; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "Tischendorf; Tischendorf." Produced by: Central-D&#00E9;pot, Asser Vi#00DF;itenkarten-Portraits von Hugo Quaas in Berlin, Leipziger Strasse 125.
    Scholars; cartes-de-visite; Tischendorf, Constantin von, 1815-1874
  - Cousin [Victor], 1860 -- 1867; MS011.001.001.00170; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "Cousin." Produced by: CH Reutlinger, Photographe, 21 Boulevart Montmartre, 21 et 112, Rue Richelieu, 112, Paris.
    Philosophers; cartes-de-visite; Cousin, Victor, 1792-1867
  - R. K. Hagenbach [?], 1860 -- 1875; MS011.001.001.00171; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "Hagenbach." Produced by: Charles deBouell.
  - D. Strauß [David Friedrich Strauss], 1865 -- 1874; MS011.001.001.00172; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "D. Strau#00DF;." Produced by: Hermann G&#00FC;nther, Hof-Photograph Seiner Majest&#00E4;t des K&#00F6;nigs u. Sr. Kgl. H. d. Prinzen Friedrich Carl, Berlin, Werderscher Markt No. 6.
  - Thiers [Adolphe], 1865 -- 1877; MS011.001.001.00173; Ullman, Sarah (Box 1)
    25. "Thiers." Produced by: Nadar, 35, Boulevart des Capucines.
  - Guizot [François], 1865 -- 1874; MS011.001.001.00174; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "Guizot." Produced by: Diséri, Photographes de S. M. L'empereur, 8 Boulevart des Italiens, Paris.
    Statesmen; Politicians; cartes-de-visite; Guizot, François
  - Coquerel [Athanase Josué], 1865 -- 1875; MS011.001.001.00175; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "Coquerel." Produced by: CH Reutlinger, Photographe, 21 Boulevart Montmartre, 21 et 112, Rue Richelieu, 112, Paris.
    Theologians; Historians; cartes-de-visite; Coquerel, Athanase, 1820-1875
  - Montalembert [Charles Forbes René de] d. 1870, 1860 -- 1870; MS011.001.001.00176; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "Montalembert; statesman, orator; wrote "Life of St. Elizabeth of Hungary" and "The Monks of the West from St. Benedict to St. Bernard."; died 1870." Produced by: E. Desmaisons, 5, Rue des Grands Augustins, Paris.
    Statesmen; Historians; image/tiff; Montalembert, Charles Forbes, comte de, 1810-1870
  - Dr. Karl Schwarz, 1860 -- 1880; MS011.001.001.00177; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "Dr. Karl Schwarz." Produced by: A. Linde, Hof-Photograph, Gotha, August-Straße 2.
    Theologians; cartes-de-visite; Schwarz, Karl, 1885-1962
  - Lacordaire [Jean-Baptiste Henri], 1855 -- 1861; MS011.001.001.00178; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. "Lacordaire; pulpit orator at Notre Dame, Paris; Dominican friar; member of the French Academy; born 1802. died 1861." Produced by: Photographie de Franck, 18, Rue Vivienne, succ le 15, Place de la Bourse.
    Preachers; cartes-de-visite; Lacordaire, Jean-Baptiste-Henri, 1802-1861
  - Alvensleben I [General Gustav von], 1860 -- 1870; MS011.001.001.00179; Unknown (Box 1)
    Franco-Prussian War, 1870-1871; Austro-Prussian War, 1866; Generals; cartes-de-visite; Alvensleben, Gustav von, 1803-1881
  - Manteuffel [Edwin Freiherr von], 1860 -- 1875; MS011.001.001.00180; Unknown (Box 1)
    Franco-Prussian War, 1870-1871; Austro-Prussian War, 1866; cartes-de-visite; Manteuffel, Edwin, Freiherr von, 1809-1885
  - [Profile of woman with hair down looking right], 1855 -- 1875; MS011.001.001.00181; Unknown (Box 1)
    25. The handwriting identifying the person pictured at the bottom of the picture is too faint to read.
  - Steinmetz [Karl Friedrich von], 1865 -- 1877; MS011.001.001.00182; Unknown (Box 1)
    Franco-Prussian War, 1870-1871; Austro-Prussian War, 1866; Generals; cartes-de-visite; Steinmetz, Karl Friedrich von, 1796-1877
  - Palikao [Charles Cousin-Montauban, Graf von (Count of)], 1865 -- 1875; MS011.001.001.00183; Unknown (Box 1)
    Generals; cartes-de-visite; Cousin-Montauban, Charles Guillaume, comte de Palikao, 1796-
  - Public Characters [List of names of 36 public figures of late 19th century], 1865 -- 1890; MS011.001.001.00184; Unknown (Box MS011 Shared 1)
    List may be in Ryder's handwriting.
- Documents inventoried in 'A Calendar of the Ryder Collection of Confederate Archives at Tufts College', 1860 -- 1940; MS011.002; 1.2 Linear Feet; 1 Digital Object(s)
  This series contains documents inventoried in 'A Calendar of the Ryder Collection of Confederate Archives at Tufts College' (The Historical Record Survey, Boston, MA 1940) that are still available. The Calendar was completely scanned and OCRd. Scans of the Calendar are included in this series so that patrons can search the calendar for cataloging information regarding all items.
  This series is organized as in the Calendar: by cataloging number chronologically arranged and undated items at end.
  - Documents inventoried in 'A Calendar of the Ryder Collection of Confederate Archives at Tufts College', 1860 -- 1865; MS011.002.001 (Box 1)
    This box contains all still available documents inventoried in 'A Calendar of the Ryder Collection of Confederate Archives at Tufts College' (The Historical Record Survey, Boston, MA 1940). The Calendar was completely scanned and OCRd. Scans of the Calendar will be exported as a finding aid of sorts so that patrons can search the calendar for cataloging information regarding all items.
  - A Calendar of the Ryder Collection of Confederate Archives at Tufts College, 1940; MS011.002.002
    Historical Records Survey (Mass.)
- Other identified Ryder material, 1861 -- 1865; MS011.003; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains other identified Ryder material.
  - Register of Treasury Notes issued under Act of April 17 1862, 1862-06-21 -- 1863-09-11; MS011.003.001.00001 (Box MS011 Shared 1)
    The bound volume is not included in the printed catalog of the Ryder collection. However, the recto page carries a book plate reading 'Tufts College Library. The Gift of Mrs. Ryder, from the library of her late husband, Rev. Wm. H. Ryder, D. D., Dec. 1888.
    The registry lists officers of treasurer, officers of register, in whose favor, date, register number/denomination (no. of each, amount of each, amount in each), description of issue, and date of acknowledgment and remarks for notes issued. Register numbers run from 1 to 30 2000, all issued June 2nd 1862 with the last date of acknowledgment and remarks from 'September 11 1863 2nd Series.' All entries are in the same handwriting.
    The box of cartes-de-visite includes a hand-written note cross-referencing this registry, MS011.001.001.00131.
    United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
  - The World, vol. V, no. 1531, New York, 1865-05-19; MS011.003.002.00001 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 1)
    Newspaper issue 'The World' was quite likely part of the original Ryder donation because page 8 contains Ref. W. H. Ryder's testimony as part of the first page article 'The Conspiracy' regarding a letter found by Ryder among the documents he collected in Richmond that documents the proposition by W. S. Oldham to burn northern cities, transports and stores and bears Jeff. Davis endorsement to look into the matter. In his testimony, Ryder described how he picked up the archives of the confederate states, their documents in the Richmond Capitol or immediately around it.
  - War [registry] commencing 18 February 1862 [Richmond registry of drafts], 1862-02-18 -- 1864-10-11; MS011.003.002.00002 (Box 2)
    Bound registry is not included in the printed inventory from 1940 'A Calendar of the Ryder Collection of Confederate Archives at Tufts College.' But given that Reverend William H. Ryder had been granted permission to pass through the lines of Richmond to collect arms, trophies, curiosities, and relics for display at the proposed North Western Sanitary Fair (see calendar entries 138-156), and that the Ryder collection contains 7 items by E. C. Elmore, the Treasurer of the Confederate States, including some individual war drafts, the registry most likely was part of the collection. Also: The box of cartes-de-visite includes a hand-written note cross-referencing this registry, MS011.001.001.00085.
    The registry begins with Feburary 1862; the number '4' is written in the top left corner possibly indicating that three previous pages/volumes are in a different registry; no pages appear to have been cut out in the beginning. Recto page includes a pasted in calendar for 1862 by J. W. Randolph, Publisher, Bookseller, Stationer and Book-Binder, 121 Main Street, Richmond, Va.
    The registry lists date, number of draft, on whom drawn, number of warrant, in whose favor, E. C. Elmore [Treasurer, Confederate States], and Sundries. The pages between October 31 1863, draft number 3635, and September 23, 1864, draft number 5217 are empty.
  - Receipts of Southern Express Company and Adams Express Company of packages to be delivered, 1861 -- 1865; MS011.003.002.00003 (Box 2)
    This material belongs to the original Ryder donation because all Adams Express Company receipts from 1865 were for W. H. Ryder.
  - Envelopes of Northwestern Sanitary Commission, 1864 -- 1865; MS011.003.002.00004 (Box 2)
    This material likely belongs to the original Ryder donation as Ryder was sent to Richmond to collect archival material for an exposition of the Northwestern Sanitary Commission in 1865.